Finding Aid for Carl H. Fischer Papers 1936-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl H. Fischer Papers 1936-1985, 1950-1970
Fischer, Carl Hahn, 1903-
1.5 linear foot
9801 Aa 2
Professor of actuary mathematics and of insurance at the University of Michigan from 1941 until 1974. Papers concern his teaching career at Michigan and consulting work on pension and social security matters.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from Mrs. Carl H. Fischer (donor number 6432 ) in June of 1989.
The papers are open for research.
Carl H. Fischer was a professor actuary mathematics and of insurance at the University of Michigan from 1941 until 1974. He received a B.S. from the Washington University in St. Louis in 1923, then a M.S. and Ph.D. from the University of Iowa in 1930 and 1932 respectively, in mathematical statistics in actuarial science. Dr. Fischer began practicing actuarial science in 1938, and became a member of the University of Michigan faculty in 1941, teaching in the departments of Mathematics and Business Administration. Before coming to the University of Michigan, Dr.Fischer had a one-year appointment at the University of Minnesota, a year with Northwestern National Life Insurance Company of Minneapolis doing actuarial research, and seven years at Wayne State University in Detroit. Starting in 1950 he was head of the Department of Insurance and Actuarial Science within the School of Business Administration at the University of Michigan. In 1974, Dr. Fischer became professor emeritus of actuary mathematics in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts and also of insurance in the Graduate School of Business Administration.
Throughout his career, Fischer was an active participant and officer in the professional organizations of his field. He served as a fellow of the Society of Actuaries, the Conference of Actuaries in Public Practice, and the Fraternal Actuarial Association, as well as being a member of the American Academy of Actuaries. He also was a member of the American Statistical Society, the Mathematical Association of America, and the Michigan Actuarial Society, and an associate of the Institute of Actuaries in Great Britain. In the course of his career, Dr. Fischer published three books and approximately 45 articles in the fields of actuarial science, pensions, and mathematics. He was a member of Sigma Xi, the Scientific Honorary, as well as Beta Gamma Sigma, the Business Administration Honorary.
Dr. Fischer lectured extensively throughout his career. He was the director and teacher at a summer actuarial program held for college students by the John Hancock Mutual Life Insurance Company of Boston on two different occasions. He taught at the Travelers Insurance Company of Hartford, Connecticut for one summer. He also was an instructor at the Hebrew University of Israel in 1965 and 1967.
Fischer served as a consultant to the United States Treasury, the General Accounting Office, and was a member of the Advisory Council for Social Security Financing. He was chairman of the committee to study the military retirement pay system for the Armed Services Committee of the United States. He also served as a consultant to Liberia to help coordinate their National Social Security and Welfare Corporation. His consulting work outside of the United States also included the Philippines where he helped to coordinate the Government Service Insurance System and the Social Security System.
Within Michigan, Dr. Fischer was the actuary for the retirement committee of the State Senate of Michigan, and also for the joint committee on Retirement for the Senate and the House. From 1948 until 1973, he was a member of the board of trustees of the city of Ann Arbor Employees Retirement System. He did consulting work for the Detroit Teachers Retirement System. Dr. Fischer died at the age of 85 in Ann Arbor, on December 21, 1988.
The Carl H., Fischer papers are organized in four series
University of Michigan
Consulting
Professional Organizations
Conference Papers/Other writings.
The Carl H. Fischer collection dates from 1936 until 1985, but primarily documents the period from 1950 until 1970. The papers mainly reflect the Dr. Fischer's professional activities within the University of Michigan School of Business, as a consultant to various organizations both American and foreign, on pension and social security matters, and as a participant in professional organizations and societies. There are thus few personal materials in the papers.
The collection is arranged into four series: University of Michigan, Consulting, Professional Organizations, and Conference Papers/Other writings. Additional information on Dr. Fischer may also be found in the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs record group of which he was director in the year 1952, and in the records of the University of Michigan School of Business Administration. Published work may be found in the University of Michigan on-line catalog.
Subjects:
Fischer, Carl Hahn, 1903-; Insurance--Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.
- University of Michigan
  Fischer's University of Michigan papers contain a melange of information on the School of Business Administration, SACUA, and the Lecture Committee. Within the School of Business Administration, Fischer was director of a study on the military retirement system, and this is well documented in the collection.
  - Lecture Committee-Oratorial Series 1954-1961 (Box 1)
  - School of Business Administration
    - Blue Cross Blue Shield Executive Program of the School of Business Administration 1954-1960 (Box 1)
    - Dean R.A. Stevenson Correspondence 1949-1960 (Box 1)
    - Deanship Committee- School of Business Administration 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Harry C. Carver Honorary Dinner 1961 (Box 1)
    - Military Retirement Study 1960-1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - School of Business Administration Faculty Correspondence 1964-1982 (Box 1)
    - School of Business Administration General Correspondence 1951-1973 (Box 1)
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs 1949-1952 (Box 1)
- Consulting
  Consulting projects comprise the bulk of the papers within the collection, documenting Fischer's involvement in international as well as domestic affairs. Of particular interest, his consulting work for the Hebrew University in Israel includes reminiscences of the political unrest occurring at that time. Also, Fischer was asked to serve a number of times as a consultant to the United States government.
  - Ann Arbor- Pension and Retirement Board 1955-1973 (Box 1)
  - Clark Equipment Company 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives of the United States (Social Security System) 1967 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Teacher's Retirement Fund Reports 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - Fingerle Lumber Company 1973-1983 (Box 1)
  - Georgia Pacific Company vs. Brown Company 1975 (Box 1)
  - Israel- Hebrew University of Jerusalem 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Liberia- National Social Security and Welfare 1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - National Advisory Council on Social Security Financing 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - North Dakota Teacher's Fund for Retirement 1961-1974 (Box 1)
  - Philippine Social Security System 1954-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Treasury Department Washington 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Watkins, Ross, Waterfield, and Barnes, Inc. 1966-1975 (Box 1)
- Professional Organizations (Box 1)
  The Professional organizations series documents Fischer's active participation with a variety of actuarial and mathematics groups. The Michigan Actuarial Society papers contain the founding constitution for the society, which Fischer in part drafted.
  - Conference of Actuaries in Public Practice 1971-1985, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Fraternal Actuarial Association 1943-1980 (Box 1)
  - Institute of Mathematical Statistics 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Actuarial Society 1945-1983 (Box 1)
  - Society of Actuaries 1959-1975 (Box 1)
- Conference Papers/Other Writings
  Throughout his career Fischer was invited to participate in conferences. The series-Conference Papers/Other Writings-includes a number of the lectures given at these meetings. The papers written by Fischer relay the importance of education within the actuarial field.
  - Actuarial Exam Study 1963 (Box 2)
  - Actuarial School Study 1967 (Box 2)
  - Actuarial Statistical Institute-Conference on Ratemaking 1954 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Chartered Life Underwriters-Fixed Dollar Policy Cash Value 1961 (Box 2)
  - Book Reviews 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - Interest Rate Assumption Papers 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Foundation of Health Welfare and Pension Plans, Inc. 1958-1973 (Box 2)
  - The Institute of Gerontology-The Economics of Aging: Towards 2001 1975 (Box 2)
  - Russell Reagh paper 1973-1974 (Box 2)